Well good morning everyone. I am delighted
to welcome you to the State Department
for the beginning of the 7th Annual Strategic
and Economic Dialogue and the Sixth
Consultation on the People to People Exchange.
We have a lot of ground to cover this morning,
a very very full agenda so we want to get
right to it. The first speaker is a friend of mine
for forty years and reminded us a few minutes
ago we served together for years on the
Foreign Relations Committee, he was my
chairman and now our Vice President
of the United States. He was certainly
one of the most knowledgeable
and accomplished leaders on foreign affairs
and I might add was almost always
ahead of the curve on most of the issues
facing us during the time when we
were in the Senate. So, my pleasure
SECRETARY KERRY: I welcome my friend,
the Vice President of the United States,
Joe Biden.
(Applause.)
VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN: Mr. Secretary, thanks
for letting us in your house. I appreciate
being able to be here. And with Secretary
Lew, I just say to our Chinese friends, I
notice you looking at the Secretary on crutches
and our Secretary of Commerce on crutches
– it’s a difficult job in Washington.
(Laughter.) We play it very – Hank Paulson
can tell you it’s a very tough place right
now. And I just want you to understand that
and why – that’s why they’re so committed
to this relationship.
Vice Premier Liu and Vice Premier Wang, State
Councilor Yang – it’s good to see you
again. We’ve spent a lot of time together.
And we each have been – all of whom have
been designated special representatives of
President Xi. I’m really honored to welcome
the entire Chinese delegation for the seventh
U.S.-China Strategic Economic Dialogue and
the sixth U.S.-China Consultation on People-to-People
Exchanges. And I want to thank Ambassador
Cui and Ambassador Baucus – it’s good
to see you, Max; welcome home – for being
here today. And I’d be remiss if I didn’t
recognize other members of the Cabinet. Secretary
Moniz is here as well as Secretary Pritzker,
who I already referenced, and Ambassador Froman
and Administrator McCarthy. And it’s – they
all are deeply involved and deeply committed
to this dialogue.
Four years ago in Beijing, then-Vice President
Xi observed, “If one is to have a full view
of the scenery, one needs to cast his eyes
to the far horizon.” Well, that’s what
we need to be doing here today – cast our
eyes to the far horizon. And we need to be
honest and direct about where we’ve been,
what lies on the horizon for the relationship
that will in many ways define the 21st century
for the remainder of the world.
It’s been ten years since then-Deputy Secretary
of State Robert Zoellick called on China to
become what he referred to as a responsible
stakeholder. He said all nations conduct diplomacy
to promote their national interest. Responsible
stakeholders go further; they recognize that
the international system sustains their peaceful
prosperity, so they work to sustain that system.
And under President Xi, as China’s interests
and capabilities have grown increasingly global,
China has indeed taken some important steps
in that direction.
For example, you have served as a partner
to curb nuclear activities in Iran and North
Korea. You’ve taken concrete actions to
address climate change, setting ambitious
climate goals at home. You’ve committed
to let the market play a greater role in your
economy, which will contribute to a stronger
and more sustainable growth in the global
economy. You supported efforts at the United
Nations to combat radical terrorism, to stem
the ability of extremist groups like ISIL
to recruit, and so much more. Chinese medical
personnel worked side by side with Americans
to fight Ebola and set up hospitals in Sierra
Leone. And China has been a leading contributor
to the United Nations peacekeeping operations
and has assisted in efforts to bring lasting
peace and stability in both Afghanistan and
the Sudan.
These are welcome actions that impact in a
very positive way the growth and security
of China, but also the region and the world.
And I believe that the future of China’s
success and global influence is directly tied
to the extent to which it acts as a responsible
stakeholder. Essential to this is continuing
to find new ways to work together even as
we manage future competition in a responsible
way. We must all embrace the role of responsible
competitor as well, helping to create and
uphold a playing field that is level, fair,
and transparent – a field where the rules
apply equally not only to the United States
and China, but to all responsible competitors
regardless of their size.
The rule-based order that emerged in the 20th
century has served the world extremely well,
and, I would respectfully suggest, including
China. It provided the ballast for remarkable
peace and prosperity that ensued after the
war. And we’d be foolish today to hastily
discard or ignore all of it. But we have to
recognize that some of the rules, such as
environmental and labor standards, have to
be updated in the 21st century. Some institutions,
such as the International Monetary Fund, they
should be updated as well and revised to reflect
the world as it is, not as it was.
And there’s an urgent need to agree on a
rule-based system for rapidly evolving areas
ranging from cyber space to outer space – a
new set of rules. Together, collaboratively,
we have an obligation – China and the United
States – to shape these rules. And let me
be clear: The United States believes strongly
that whenever possible, China needs to be
at the table as these new rules are written.
Responsible competition, adhering to these
common rules – both old and new – in my
view will be the essential ingredient necessary
to manage areas of disagreement, and to build
the long-term sustainable U.S.-China relationship.
As President Xi has said, “There’s competition
in cooperation.” Yet such competition is
healthy, based on mutual learning and mutual
reinforcement. It’s a fundamental sense.
It is conducive to our common development.
I believe that. The President of the United
States believes that. The Secretary of State
believes that. And as I’ve told President
Xi on multiple occasions I’ve had to be
with him over the last several years, we – the
United States – we welcome fair and healthy
competition. Quite frankly, you’ve awakened
us. We got a little slow. We were a little
– I know my colleagues don’t like my saying
this, but the truth is we got a little – how
can I say it – too comfortable in the last
part of the 20th century. It awakened the
competitive spirit that’s stamped into the
DNA of every American, naturalized as well
as native born. And a lot of them are Chinese,
I might add.
I believe the United States of America is
not only well positioned to thrive, but to
contribute to the economic growth of the entire
world as we grow. We’re in the midst in
the United States of an energy transformation
that has positioned us as the epicenter of
the world’s energy sector over the 21st
century, including renewable energy. We have
the finest research universities in the world
that educate millions of Americans and the
brightest minds from around the world, including
China. We’re the top destination for immigration
from entrepreneurs, scientists, academics,
and artists who bring creative solutions and
want to create an open and welcoming environment.
It’s the creative edge we have, being as
open as we are to immigration.
The best of the world make their way here.
It’s not that someone sits around a table
in Southeast Asia or Africa or Latin America
and says, “I’ve got a great idea. Why
don’t we sell everything we have, pick up,
get smuggled into a country that doesn’t
want us? We’re going to have fun, aren’t
we? This is wonderful.” The truth is the
people who make those judgments are people
with courage and vision, optimism, innovation.
So we have benefited from the openness of
our system over the last 200 and some years.
We also in the United States protect innovation
from those – the innovation that emanates
from those great minds – through strong
protection of intellectual property and the
rule of law. Fair competition not only spurs
our companies to develop better products and
services; it spurs economic growth around
the world. On a level playing field, our growth
contributes to yours, and your growth in China
contributes to ours. Your nation has opened
up to the world and you have lifted 500 million
people out of poverty, one of the most remarkable
occurrences in human history – 500 million
people out of poverty. Your traditions of
scholarship, philosophy, entrepreneurship,
and ambition are now paired with an increasingly
educated public, including the education of
millions of engineers and scientists from
your finest universities.
The economic dynamism of your nation has supported
the prosperity and growth of not only China,
but throughout Asia. The future contributions
of a successful, open, and collaborative China
that embraces the responsibility of a stakeholder
and a responsible competitor have tremendous
potential for all of us, the whole world.
But any country that relies on unhealthy practices
to undermine healthy competition with others
ultimately limits itself. There’s sort of
like – there’s new rules of economics
in the 21st century not set by any nation;
they’re like rules of physics. There are
certain things that have to exist for nations
to truly meet their potential. Responsible
competitors help to sustain the system where
research and development are rewarded, where
intellectual property is protected, and the
rule of law is upheld, because nations that
use cyber technology as an economic weapon
or profits from the theft of intellectual
property are sacrificing tomorrow’s gains
for short-term gains today. They diminish
the innovative drive and determination of
their own people when they do not reward and
protect intellectual property.
Responsible companies adhere to international
law and work together to keep international
sea lanes open for unimpaired commerce. Eighty
percent of all the commerce today is on the
back of a ship somewhere floating on the oceans
– 80 percent of all the world’s economy.
The notion of sea lanes being open and protected
is even more crucial today than any time in
human history because of the interconnectedness
of the world and global economy. Because nations
that disregard diplomacy and use coercion
and intimidation to settle disputes or turned
a blind eye to aggression of others only invite
instability and undermine the collaborative
goals of the international community. And
I can think of no nation that will greater
benefit from international – an international
economic collaboration than China and the
United States.
And responsible competitors draw on the talents
of every part of their societies. This is
not lecturing; please do not misunderstand
me. This is just one of those economic rules,
like rules of physics in the 21st century
– protecting the rights and voices of women,
minorities, journalists, civil society, religious
leaders; allowing nongovernmental organizations
and educational groups to operate without
harassment, intimidation, or detention. In
short, they respect human rights not just
because it’s the right thing to do, but
because it’s absolutely economically necessary.
I think it’s originally, actually, in a
Chinese expression: Women hold up half the
sky. Women hold up half the sky. Nations that
do not take advantage of the populations – and
I’m not directing this at any particular
country – any nation that doesn’t take
advantage of it is squandering their potential,
because as surely as people cannot live without
blood coursing through their veins, societies
cannot thrive without the full participation
of all its citizens. Just like the basic rules
of physics, as I said, there are underlying
tenets of fair and responsible competition
that comprise the path to stability and prosperity
in the 21st century for all nations.
And let me be crystal clear, and I know my
friends and I have become – have made some
friendships in your leadership. Let me be
clear: We do not fear China’s rise. We want
to see China rise, to continue to rise in
a responsible way that will benefit you most,
China, because you have an important role
to play. A rising China can be a significant
asset for the region and the world, and selfishly,
for the United States.
China, like all nations in Asia, benefits
from stability and prosperity – a stability
and prosperity that, quite frankly, has been
maintained over – since the end of the World
War II by the United States of America for
60 years. We’re going to continue to play
a role for decades to come, but don’t misunderstand
it: We are a Pacific nation. 7,632 miles of
our shoreline breaks on the Pacific Ocean.
We are a Pacific nation. What happens anywhere
in the Pacific affects the United States as
much as – more than any other portion of
the world. And now we are a Pacific power,
and we’re going to continue to remain a
Pacific power. To respond to the changing
world, the Administration has set in motion
an institutionalized rebalance policy of the
Asian Pacific region, not to contain but to
expand all of our opportunities.
We believe this is important because the Pacific
and every nation along its shore from Chile
to China will form the economic engine that
drives the economies of the 21st century.
That’s where the action will be. As part
of that rebalanced strategy, we’ve strengthened
and modernized our alliances and our partnerships
throughout the region. As part of that strategy,
we have deepened our support for important
regional institutions like ASEAN, and we’re
continuing to work on the Trans-Pacific Partnership,
which I predict we will succeed in getting
done – the most progressive trade agreement
in American history, and history, period.
It boosts economic growth at home and abroad.
And as part of that strategy, we’re working
to build more constructive and productive
ties with China. But we all know this relationship
is complicated and consequential, to say the
least. And we all know, like a good marriage,
it requires an awful lot of hard, hard work,
an awful lot of attention. In 1979, I was
a young junior senator and I was invited to
go to China with a group of senior, important
senators – the first delegation to visit
China after normalization and to meet with
Deng Xiaoping. We had an opportunity to spend
a considerable amount of time with him. I
was criticized when I got back home because
I was asked what did I think, and I said,
“I think that a rising and peaceful China
could provide an extremely positive incentive
for the United States and the world.” I
still believe that. I believed it in 1979
that that was possible, and I believe it’s
even more likely today.
Then as now, I recognized that our two countries
had clear disagreements on important issues.
But that’s not a new phenomenon. The animating
logic of our relationship is also not new.
Both sides accept that we each gain by working
together where our interests align, and addressing
our differences candidly and constructively
where they do not. And there are places where
they will not align.
In reviewing the course that has led us to
today, I think it’s worth recalling that
both our countries have gone through considerable
changes since 1979, even since we met in the
first Strategic & Economy Dialogue in 2009.
For our part, the United States has entered
a period of renewal, optimism, and new strength.
Thanks to the aggressive actions we took to
stimulate our economy and to stabilize our
financial sector in the wake of the recession,
our economy has gone from recession to recovery
to resurgence. Twelve point six million private
sector jobs added over those years; 63 straight
months of employment growth; $30 trillion
in household wealth has been added back since
the President and I took office. Unemployment
is down from 10 percent to 5.5 percent, and
I predict we’ll go lower. U.S. exports are
at record levels. U.S. businesses have served
as the Asia Pacific’s biggest source of
foreign direct investment. U.S. businesses
have invested over $620 billion in investment
stock in the region just in 2013.
And as we grow, we acknowledge our depending
– our deepening economic interdependence.
China is the largest destination for U.S.
exports – you all know that – outside
of North America. Our country engages – our
countries engage in over half a trillion dollars
in trade every year, and it’s destined to
grow. Because of the strong economic ties,
China’s success benefits our own, as I said,
just as our economic resurgence supports China’s
growth. In just the last year or two, for
example, China has made some changes to promote
Chinese household consumption and allow more
market-determined interest rates. As your
third plenum laid out, there was a need to
open the economy to private sector competition,
implement market-based exchange rates, and
to grant greater market access to foreign
investors. That was your decision, not ours.
Your plenum made that judgment.
We recognize the advances that China has made,
and we encourage further progress in this
effort to reform the economy. And we know
the remarkable potential of the Chinese people.
As we build toward the future that realizes
the full potential of both our countries,
success in the Strategic & Economic Dialogue
and the Consultation on People-to-People Exchanges
is critical.
Over the past few days, you have had an opportunity
to make substantive progress on nonproliferation,
strong and balanced economic growth, trade
and investment, climate change, energy, environment,
ocean conservation, maritime security, cyber
issues, human rights, sustainable development,
public health, education. We’re not going
to solve all these problems in this meeting
or in multiple meetings, but we have to be
committed to working towards solutions in
each of these areas.
I need not tell you all that are participating
we have a lot of hard work to do, but we have
to keep at it day after day after day after
day. This relationship is just too important.
Not only do we depend on it, but the world
depends on our mutual success. To put it bluntly,
the world is depending on those of you in
this room to continue to work through those
issues. There’s an old Chinese proverb that
says one generation plants a tree, the next
enjoys the shade. Today we gather in the shade
of a tree planted by those visionaries on
both sides of the Pacific who joined hands
a generation ago, and now we have to plant
additional trees together, today, so the generations
that follow in both of our countries and around
the world can grow and flourish in the shade,
prosperity, security of a new friendship.
There will be intense competition. We will
have intense disagreements. That’s the nature
of international relations. But there are
important issues where we don’t see eye
to eye, but it doesn’t mean we should stop
working hand in hand because we don’t see
eye to eye. There was a famous American politician
who we all loved – his name was Tip O’Neill
– who was speaker of the House. He said
all politics is local. Well, I’m getting
old enough and I’ve hung around long – as
long as he had in the House and Senate and
in politics, and I’m going to presume to
try to improve on that. I believe that all
politics, especially international politics,
is personal. It’s all personal. And – because
only by building a personal relationship – that’s
the only vehicle by which you can build trust.
Doesn’t mean you have to even like the other
person, but it has to be a personal relationship
where you understand what the other guy needs,
the other woman needs, and what you need,
and work through it. That’s the only way
to build trust.
Because of President Hu and President Obama,
I had the opportunity to spend scores of hours
with President Xi when he was vice president.
He even was nice enough to see me for five
hours when he was president. I think I know
him. We know him. We know his aspirations
for your country.
So as I told her last time we met, I’m particularly
grateful that Vice Premier Liu is – for
everything she’s done to help build the
face relationship that, as a Chinese co-chair,
the Consultation on People-to-People Exchanges
– it’s important. The exchange has led
to concrete progress in our relationship from
an increased number of Americans studying
in China to a program connecting young, professional
scientists through in-person exchanges. These
accomplishments are critical to expanding
cooperation in areas such as the arts, education,
women’s issues, science and technology.
So I want to thank her again for her leadership,
and I want to thank Secretary Kerry for the
hard work he’s put in this effort as well.
And it’s now my honor to introduce premier
– am I doing the introduction? I am, okay.
(Laughter.) I was about to take advantage
of this opportunity, but Liu Yandong as our
next speaker. Thank you. (Applause.)
VICE PREMIER LIU: (Via interpreter) Vice President
Biden, Secretary Kerry, Secretary Jacob Lew,
ladies and gentlemen, dear friends, good morning.
I want to thank Vice President Biden for his
speech. During Vice President Biden’s visit
to China, the Chinese people were very impressed
and in his speech he particularly emphasized
the importance of China-U.S. relations from
a global context. He talked about common interests
of our two countries, the common challenges,
and our respective responsibilities. And that
fully shows the leaders of the United States
and the American Government the high level
of importance they attach to the relations
with China. So I want to thank the Vice President
for that.
According to the agreement of the two countries,
the seventh S&ED and the sixth CPE have a
joint opening ceremony this morning. This
is the first time that the two mechanisms
and three dialogues are held concurrently
in the United States. It is of very special
and important significance. Vice Premier Wang
Yang and State Councilor Yang Jiechi and I
are particularly happy to be back in Washington,
D.C. again, which is a very beautiful city,
and to co-chair respectively with Secretary
Kerry and Secretary Lew for the two mechanisms.
Representatives from both sides are gathered
together, and the scale is unprecedented.
We have 13 ministers and 40 vice minister-level
officials from the Chinese side. And that
shows both sides take very seriously our bilateral
relations.
First of all, I wish to, on behalf of Vice
Premier Wang Yang and State Councilor Yang
Jiechi and all the entire Chinese delegation,
our appreciation to the thoughtful and meticulous
arrangements made by the U.S. side. (Applause.)
President Xi Jinping takes this S&ED and CPE
very close to his heart, and he asked me and
Vice Premier Wang Yang and State Councilor
Yang Jiechi to bring a message for President
Obama and convey his greetings and best wishes
to President Obama, Vice President Biden,
the two secretaries and all the colleagues
from the U.S. side. He believes that the new
model of major country relations featuring
mutual benefits, win-win cooperation, non-confrontation
is the priority of China’s foreign policy.
Facing complicated and volatile international
situation, China and the United States should
work together. They can work together in a
wide range of areas. The two sides should
keep the bilateral ties on the right track.
As long as our two countries adopt an overall
perspective, respect and accommodate each
other’s core interests and be committed
to a constructive approach to reduce misunderstanding
and miscalculations, we can manage our differences
and maintain our common interests.
He expressed a hope that the two teams will
keep up the good work to take full advantage
of the role of the S&ED and CPE to promote
mutual trust and cooperation between the two
countries and to ensure that the bilateral
ties will bring benefits to people of the
two countries and people of the entire world.
Ladies and gentlemen, dear friends, the Consultation
on People-to-People Exchange together with
political mutual trust and business ties are
intertwined and reinforcing each other. They
form the three major pillars of China-U.S.
relations. Since 2010 when the CPE mechanism
was established, China and the United States
have held five rounds of consultations and
achieved nearly 300 concrete deliverables.
I’m happy to see that the people-to-people
exchange between our two countries today has
expanded to cover more areas, as Vice President
Biden said – that the CPE from four major
areas add to the first round of the consultation
now covers seven areas, and this time we’ll
add public health into the dynamics.
We have now involved multiple stakeholders,
and it is shortening the distance between
people of our two countries and increased
mutual trust and friendship. And this mechanism
is now showing its increasingly unique charm
and important role and has forcefully promoted
steady and sound growth of China-U.S. relations.
As we say in China, even a thousand-story
tower starts from piles of earth, and in today’s
world we’re living in a global village and
countries have become a community of common
destiny and intertwined interests. The building
of the new model of major country relations
not only needs efforts from politicians and
diplomats, but more importantly, understanding
and support from our people, especially those
at the grassroot level. The theme of the CPE
this year is exchanges, mutual learning for
win-win cooperation. Our two countries will
reach a series of practical and concrete outcomes
in education, science and technology, culture,
sports, women, youth, and health.
We are looking forward to working together
with the U.S. side to build more platforms
for mutual understanding of our two peoples
and create conditions for mutual learning
between civilizations from East and West,
so that hundred millions of students, scientists,
artists, and people from different walks of
life, including our women and young people,
to feel and share the joy of exchanges and
harvests so that this new model of major country
relations of China and the United States will
have greater warmth, resilience, depth, and
breadth.
Here I wish to express my belief and hope
that the 7th S&ED and 6th CPE will be a complete
success. Now I would like to invite the American
chair of the 6th CPE, Secretary Kerry, to
deliver his speech. Secretary Kerry with his
wisdom, capabilities has impressed all of
us deeply, especially in the 5th consultation
in Beijing. The music he played with a Chinese
instrument pipa attracted 6 million Chinese
fans. And now I would like to give the floor
to Secretary Kerry. (Applause.)
SECRETARY KERRY: Mr. Vice President, thank
you very much. We appreciate your comments
enormously. Vice Premier Liu, thank you very
much. I’m looking for the royalties on those
6 million fans. (Laughter.) State Councilor
Yang and Vice Premier Wang, distinguished
guests, members of the Chinese and American
delegations, and I particularly want to warmly
welcome both our ambassadors – the ambassador
from China – Ambassador Cui and my friend
Max Baucus back here. And I particularly also
am happy to see our fellow members of the
President’s cabinet here, and I think the
numbers of participants really underscores
the importance of this meeting.
This is the 3rd Strategic & Economic Dialogue
in which I’ve had the pleasure of participating
directly, and I’m confident that we’re
going to be able to take full advantage of
the chance to expand our bilateral cooperation.
We particularly look forward to September,
when President Xi will pay a state visit to
the United States, to Washington, and we’re
confident that when our presidents meet again,
if we do our work well over the course of
these next months, we will be able to advance
this relationship.
As the Vice President noted in his remarks,
we have taken a number of very positive steps
over the course of the past year. These include,
perhaps first and foremost, an historic announcement
on climate change. In addition, nurturing
confidence between our militaries as we have
increased our mil-to-mil engagement, extending
visa validation reciprocity, working very
solidly together as partners in the P5+1 negotiations
on Iran, and helping our friends in West Africa
combat the deadly Ebola virus. And I had a
chance last night – we had a wonderful dinner
at Mount Vernon last night, a very open and
freewheeling discussion in the course of that,
but we really were able to isolate those things
on which we differ and talk about them in
reasonable ways, but most importantly get
excited about the possibilities of cooperation
between these two great nations.
We believe that the steps we’ve taken over
the course of the last year are important
in and of themselves. But they also have a
larger value, because when other nations see
China and the United States working together,
it tends to galvanize their own efforts. It
tends to increase their focus on similar issues.
So more and more I think we have both decided
that our partnership is an essential starting
point to the resolution of global problems,
and that this partnership can indeed become
even more important in terms of providing
a better sense of structure and order in a
world where there is an increasing sense of,
at least in some places, disorder or even
chaos.
This week, in these next two days, we have
a very, very full agenda. It includes building
on the progress that we’ve already made
in the field of sustainable energy cooperation,
the environment, and curbing greenhouse gas
emissions. This topic alone, frankly, validates
our dialogue, because unless our countries
lead on these issues, meaningful gains are
simply not going to happen. And if you take
the judgment of scientists with the seriousness
that one should, we all understand the serious
consequences of not achieving progress.
We’ve made a good start, but we all understand
we have to do more within and beyond our borders.
We have to drive home the urgency of growing
economically in ways that are green and clean.
And as Secretary Moniz and Secretary Pritzker
and Secretary Lew and all of us will underscore,
the energy market is the biggest market in
the world. It can drive all of our economies,
and it is a growing market as we go from some
six billion people to nine billion people
on the face of this planet – all of whom
will be consumers of energy.
So we believe that we can contribute to shared
prosperity by coordinating in addition on
development policy, which is something that
our countries have never done before. This
is something that State Councilor Yang Jiechi
began a discussion on over a year ago in Boston,
and President Obama and President Xi have
agreed and put focus on it with a determination
that if the United States and China could
together find development projects on which
we could cooperate, we could exponentially
leverage that much more positive outcome.
On the strategic track, we will review the
possibilities for further cooperation on Afghanistan;
the Iran nuclear negotiations, which we go
to towards the end of this week and are reaching
a pivotal moment; on counterterrorism and
the Middle East. We will talk about regional
security in the Asia Pacific, including stability
in the Korean Peninsula, and the need to reduce
tensions rather than add to them in the South
China Sea and the East China Seas. We will
devote a special session to coordinating oceans
policy, which is hugely important environmentally,
economically, and obviously from the perspective
of international order and law. And we look
forward to a very frank discussion of cyber
security and other ongoing concerns, such
as internet freedom, human rights, and religious
liberty.
Now, we are aware – obviously, and both
speakers have already referenced this – that
we will not agree on all issues. No nations
agree on every issue. But we do not accept
that a narrowing of the differences is beyond
our reach. The dialogue between those who
already see eye to eye is not a particularly
interesting or necessary dialogue. But the
discussion that – a discussion that merely
restates longstanding positions becomes pretty
sterile. That’s not what we’re looking
for here. We’re not satisfied with simply
maintaining the status quo. Our relationship
is dynamic and it has grown and matured steadily
in the past decades, and most notably in recent
years. We each have a stake in continuing
that momentum.
One way to do that is through the sixth edition
of the Consultation on the People-to-People
Exchange. Contacts between our citizens in
the arenas of business, science, technology,
athletics, and the empowerment of women work
best when they are fully reciprocal and unfettered.
These contacts can take many forms – from
technical workshops, sports competitions,
to online conversations and the travel of
students back and forth across the Pacific.
Frankly, this is diplomacy on a retail basis,
and it’s some of the most important diplomacy
that we can do. It’s how we forge a comprehensive
partnership out of smaller friendships. And
this year, for the first time we will be focusing
on cooperation in the area of health. And
right now, as you imagine, that’s not a
bad topic for me. (Laughter.)
My colleagues, if we are going to reap a harvest
from the opportunities that are staring us
in the face – and they are many – than
we really need to be honest with each other.
And I hope that frankness is going to be the
hallmark of our conversations over the next
two days. We can’t promise one thing and
then do something else. We’ve got to live
up to the commitments that we make and the
world is looking to China and the United States
to fulfill commitments. That’s how we will
build a foundation for real cooperation, and
that is why we established the Strategic & Economic
Dialogue and the Consultation on People-to-People
Exchange in the first place. That is why we
are here today.
This is serious business. Last night, State
Councilor Yang Jiechi and I referenced the
fact that at any given moment, there are a
lot of conversations taking place in the world.
But at this particular moment, given the stakes,
given the interests, given the possibilities,
this is one of the most important conversations
that could be taking place. There is never
a routine moment in U.S.-China relations.
Every meeting matters. Every day matters.
And every decision matters, because of the
consequences that it may have for future choices.
So I echo the words of Vice President Biden:
We have to make the absolute most of these
two days. And as I look around this room at
the serious people who have gathered here
to do so, I’m confident that we’re going
to make this a success. I thank all of you
for taking part in this effort. A special
thanks to Vice President Biden for having
joined us this morning to kick this off, and
tomorrow President Obama is very much looking
forward to meeting with the delegation and
having a chance to close out this conversation.
So at this time it is my pleasure to ask you
all to join me in welcoming Vice Premier Wang.
(Applause.)
VICE PREMIER WANG: (Via interpreter) I don’t
want to enjoy the treatment enjoyed by Secretary
Kerry. I don’t have to stay there.
Secretary Kerry, Secretary Lew, ladies and
gentlemen, this round of dialogue precedes
President Xi’s first state visit to the
United States and is the last round of the
S&ED held in the United State during President
Obama’s term of office. This has conferred
a special and important mission upon our dialogue,
which involves hopes and expectations of both
presidents. The Chinese team will work with
our U.S. colleagues to lay a solid foundation
for a successful visit by President Xi and
add a mark of success for the Obama Administration.
In the past seven years, the S&ED has grown
broader and stronger, acquiring a richer agenda
and better format, and producing more fruitful
results. The two rounds of economic dialogue
have been held by the current governments,
yielding over 170 outcomes in various fields.
Substantive progress has been made on major
issues, including BIT negotiation, climate
change, and ITA expansion, injecting positive
energy to China-U.S. relations and common
development of the world. Some outcomes may
seem insignificant at this stage, but once
nurtured by the fountain of opportunity, these
seedlings will grow into large fields.
This is not just an expectation for the future,
but also a summary of the past. More importantly,
the dialogue mechanism itself shows the commitment
of both governments to work together for win-win
results. As such, it is conducive to boosting
the confidence of people and companies of
the two countries in developing closer cooperation
and exchanges. Today more than 10,000 Chinese
and Americans travel across the Pacific every
day, and the number keeps growing at a double-digit
rate. Two-way trade has exceeded U.S. $550
billion, and China has become one of the fastest-growing
export markets for the United States. U.S.
exports to China have helped to create nearly
1 million jobs in the U.S. Accumulated mutual
investment topped U.S. $120 billion. And Chinese
businesses have so far made investment in
44 states of America, with total investment
reaching U.S. $46 billion and creating 80,000
jobs for America, and the numbers are still
growing.
With such convergence of the two countries’
interests, which has gone beyond many people’s
imagination, neither of us could afford the
cost of noncooperation or even all-out confrontation.
Our high-level, multidimensional dialogue
is a testament to the greater maturity of
relations between our two nations. Dialogue
helps us understand each other’s thinking
and get to the crux of how to make cooperation
work and better handle differences.
On some issues, perhaps, consensus still eludes
us. However, talking to each other could help
pave the way to finding a solution, or at
least help keep our differences under control.
Although dialogue may fall short of expectation,
and sometimes nothing much is achieved, leaving
everybody unhappy, yet it would always be
more preferable than confrontation. Some people
believe that the Thucydides trap between major
countries is insurmountable. Some even want
China and the United States to confront each
other. In any case, decision-makers of both
countries must always remember that confrontation
is a negative sum game in which both sides
will pay heavy prices and the world will suffer
too.
Talking to each other does not create win-win
all the time, but both sides will lose in
a case of confrontation. Our dialogue mechanism
may not be perfect, but it is an indispensable
platform for the two countries to increase
mutual trust, deepen cooperation, and manage
differences.
History teaches us that China and the United
States must not follow the old path of confrontation
and conflict between major countries. Building
a new model of major country relations is
an effort to explore a new path towards peaceful
coexistence. This path may not be smooth and
the journey could be bumpy, but as a great
Chinese writer said: “Originally there is
no path – but as people walk down the same
track and again, a path appears.” I’m
convinced that we are on the right track.
Thank you. (Applause.)
And now, I welcome my rival, Secretary Jacob
Lew, to take the floor.
SECRETARY LEW: Good morning. I’d like to
join Vice President Biden and Secretary Kerry
in welcoming Vice Premier Liu, Vice Premier
Wang, State Councilor Yang, and the entire
Chinese delegation to Washington for this
seventh meeting of the Strategic & Economic
Dialogue. I’d also like to welcome all of
the members of the Chinese delegation, our
cabinet and Administration members, and our
two ambassadors who are here with us today.
I particularly welcome the opportunity to
co-chair our economic track discussions with
Vice Premier Wang with whom I’ve worked
so closely over the last several years and
who’s played a central role in strengthening
our bilateral cooperation. The Strategic & Economic
Dialogue is a key mechanism for generating
practical cooperation on issues across our
relationship, and it’s led to important,
tangible results for both sides. It also provides
an opportunity for frank, high-level discussions
on areas where we have concerns and need to
manage our differences and to work through
issues to prepare for a productive leaders
meeting in September.
Over the next two days, we will address a
range of economic issues of importance to
the American and Chinese people. These include
promoting strong, sustainable, and balanced
growth; enhancing financial sector reform
and stability; and emphasizing our joint responsibilities
in upholding high governance and standards
in the international economic system. We’ll
also discuss candidly and work to make progress
on areas of concern, such as cyber security,
barriers to open trade and investment, and
exchange rate reform. Together, the United
States and China account for a third of global
gross domestic product, and nearly 40 percent
of recent global growth.
We have an enormous stake in each other’s
economic performance. As the world’s two
largest economies, a mutually beneficial economic
relationship is of great importance not only
to the prosperity of our own peoples but to
the health and development of the global economy.
The U.S. economy has strengthened in the past
year led by strong private demand. Though
growth slowed somewhat in early 2015, in part
due to temporary factors, the near-term outlook
in momentum remains strong. Improved labor
market conditions, along with the recent sharp
decline in energy prices, have been a boon
to consumers, helping to lift consumer confidence
to its highest level in a decade.
Continued strong growth in China, particularly
growth based increasingly on domestic demand,
is also essential to global growth and prosperity.
We support China’s economic reform agenda,
including efforts to allow the market to play
a more decisive role in the economy and rely
more on consumption to drive China’s economic
growth. As part of these reforms, it’s critical
that China continue to move to a more market-determined
exchange rate and a more transparent exchange
rate policy.
We have a shared interest and a joint responsibility
to pursue policies that support the global
economy, as well as uphold and continue to
improve the global economic and financial
architecture. This includes responsibilities
to abide by certain standards of behavior
within cyber space. We remain deeply concerned
about government-sponsored cyber theft from
companies and commercial sectors. The United
States and China have a shared interest in
ensuring that the internet continues to drive
growth and prosperity worldwide. We look forward
to discussing these matters further.
China has a significant role in the global
economic and financial architecture, and we
hope China will work with us to maintain and
advance high standards in multilateral institutions.
This is especially critical as we head into
China’s G20 host year. We must work to achieve
a mutually beneficial bilateral economic relationship,
including through a trade and investment relationship
that provides a level playing field, promotes
innovation, and supports jobs and growth.
We must work together to show leadership on
financing to combat climate change. We look
forward to working with China as it continues
to deepen its domestic financial market reforms
and becomes more integrated into the global
financial system.
Our goal is to continue to make concrete,
tangible progress on our respective issues
of concern in order to deliver mutual benefits
to the United States and China. We intend
to use this forum, built up over the past
decade and involving engagement at the most
senior levels of both of our governments,
to tackle difficult issues – issues that,
if left unaddressed, would hinder the bilateral
relationship.
I’m confident that we will continue to make
the kind of concrete progress during the seventh
round of the S&ED that we’ve made in the
past. We look to productive and cooperative
discussions over the next two days as we address
the mutual challenges that we face. And with
that, please join me in welcoming our next
speaker, State Councilor Yang. (Applause.)
STATE COUNCILOR YANG: (Via interpreter) Secretary
Kerry, Secretary Lew, Vice Premier Liu, Vice
Premier Wang, ladies and gentlemen, friends:
It gives me great pleasure to have this opportunity
to attend the seventh round of S&ED and attend
the joint opening session for the seventh
S&ED and sixth CPE. I see many colleagues
and friends that I know, but I also spot some
new friends among the audience, so it gives
me great pleasure to meet with all of you.
We live in a complex and fast-changing world
with new opportunities and new challenges
emerging all the time. Countries are seeking
reform, development and incorporation to keep
up with the trend of the times. China and
the United States, as the world’s biggest
developing country and the biggest developed
country, need to stand high and look far under
the changing circumstances, stay committed
to China-U.S. relations, and work together
for world peace and development of all countries.
Maybe there aren’t as many skyscrapers in
Washington as those in New York, but here
in Washington, D.C. we still can stand high
and look far, and let us work together to
build a new model of major country relationship.
Why? Because our two countries are countries
with major influence in the world, and both
of us are committed to promoting peace, stability
and development of the world. Our two countries
are in the Pacific region. At last year’s
APEC Economic Leaders’ Meeting held in Beijing,
we reached agreement to have an FTAAP. We
hope that we can stay the course for the free
trade agreement in the Asia Pacific. Both
our two countries believe that we need to
uphold the purpose and principles of the UN
charter, and take those purpose and principles
as the norms governing international relations.
China is a participant in promoting the international
order and we have benefited from the international
order. We will work with the United States
and indeed, for that matter, all other countries
in the world to push for a more just and fair
international order. President Xi said that
we need to forge a community of shared destiny
for all mankind. We follow the principles
of sincerity, affinity, real benefit and inclusiveness
for our neighborhood. The Asia Pacific is
the most dynamic region in the world. In this
region, China and the United States should
work together. We hope that we can see even
better economic growth in the United States
because it serves the interests of all countries
around the world.
Just now, Vice President Biden, Secretary
Kerry and Secretary Lew all mentioned that
they want to see economic growth in China,
and they want to see closer business and trade
cooperation between the two countries. So
China’s development also serves the peace
and stability of the region and beyond. China
is committed to the path of peaceful development,
and China also hopes that other countries
around the world will also follow the course
of peaceful development. We believe that countries
around the world, regardless of their size
and their strength, are equal members of the
international community. We are committed
to promoting democracy and international relations.
This year marks the 70th anniversary of the
founding of the United Nations. We hope that
we can work together to uphold the outcome
of victory of the Second World War, continue
to follow norms governing international relations
with the UN charter at its core. China and
the United States opened the door to diplomatic
engagement in 1972. Despite ups and downs
in our bilateral relations, this relationship
has followed the right track in general, and
both countries have benefited from this relationship.
Areas of cooperation far outnumber the areas
of competition. With regard to competition,
I am a patriot, but I still believe that for
Chinese basket team to have a draw outcome
with the U.S. basketball team, that will be
a tall order, and vice versa for the U.S.
ping-pong team to win the Chinese ping-pong
team. That will be – that will take some
time.
So the point I’m driving at is that both
of us have our respective strengths. We need
to be mutually complementary to each other.
We need to turn competition into cooperation.
As a matter of fact, we have already started
doing so. In Asia, we are helping some developing
countries on their water conservancy projects
to improve their peoples’ lives. We are
ready to work with the U.S. in Africa and
other regions. We are promoting a strategy
of strengthening the country through science
and technology. One important aspect of this
strategy is to protect intellectual property
rights. In this regard, we stand ready for
closer cooperation with the U.S.
Our two countries have made instructions to
further China-U.S. relations under the new
situation. Our task is to make this round
a resonating success and live up to the expectations
of our presidents and the people of our two
countries. I hope that our dialogue will help
us better understand each other’s domestic
and foreign policies and view each other’s
strategic intentions in the right way, so
that we can reduce suspicion, prevent miscalculation,
and cement the foundation of our cooperation.
I hope our dialogue will help us build common
ground and work through differences on the
sensitive issues.
We need to work in the same direction, respect
and accommodate each other’s core interests
and major concerns, manage our differences
in the relevant areas, and stay on the right
track of building a new model of major country
relations between our two countries. The growing
business ties and the growing world economy
will benefit from navigation freedom across
the world. China is firmly for navigation
freedom across the world. We hope that our
two sides can work together to ensure that
the global economy can improve in the right
direction.
We need to keep the transparency of regional
trading architecture and framework and openness.
We hope that in promoting trade liberalization,
in trade in services, to have – to achieve
bigger things in this regard. We hope – we
believe that cyber security is very important.
We think that countries should work together
to develop international code of conduct for
cyber information sharing.
We will work with the United States and other
countries to work in the spirit of openness,
to properly address the relevant issues. We
hope that this round of S&ED will achieve
positive outcomes. I look forward to working
with Secretary Kerry for exchanges of views.
We hope that our dialogue will help us further
expand win-win cooperation. For example, deepening
practical cooperation on energy, environmental
protection, law enforcement, and so on. We
need to promote positive interaction and inclusive
cooperation in the Asia Pacific, and we need
to strengthen communication and coordination
on such regional hotspot issues as the Iranian
and Korean nuclear issues. We need to tap
potential of cooperation on climate change,
marine conservation, and global development.
Our work together will not only bring more
tangible benefits to our two peoples, but
also serve peace, stability, and prosperity
in the Asia Pacific and the world at large.
Like what Vice Premier Wang and Vice Premier
Liu and Secretary Kerry and Secretary Lew
– they all had their mission to introduce
the next speaker. I don’t have this task.
But I also have a glorious mission, that is
I want to thank each and every one of you
to be here for this opening session. I want
to thank you all for you contribution to China-U.S.
relationship and for the success of our S&ED
and the CPE. Thank you all. (Applause.)